<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digamias adikia, or, The first marriage of Katherine Fitzgerald (now Lady Decies) contracted in facie ecclesiæ with John Power, now Lord of Decies / asserted by Dudley Loftus ...</title>
            <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12246323</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12246323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1507:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Digamias adikia, or, The first marriage of Katherine Fitzgerald (now Lady Decies) contracted in facie ecclesiæ with John Power, now Lord of Decies / asserted by Dudley Loftus ...</title>
                  <author>Loftus, Dudley, 1619-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXVII [1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Emanuel College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage law --  England.</term>
               <term>Age of consent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56948:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56948:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΔΙΓΑΜΙΑΣ ΑΔΙΚΙΑ: OR, The firſt Marriage OF <hi>Katherine Fitzgerald,</hi> (Now Lady <hi>Decies</hi>) Contracted <hi>in Facie Eccleſiae</hi> with JOHN POWER, now Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> Aſſerted,</p>
            <p>BY DUDLY LOFTUS, D. LL. and Judge of the Prerogative Court in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If a Damſel that is betrothed to an Husband, and a Man find her in the City, and lie with her: then ye ſhall bring them both out unto the Gate of that City, and ye ſhall ſtone them with ſtones, that they die.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 22.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56948:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56948:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ARTHUR Earl of Angleſey, Lord Keeper of His Majeſties Privy-Seal, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Here preſent to your Lordſhips View and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage the enſuing Argument of Dr. <hi>Loftus</hi> on the Caſe of the Lord of <hi>Decies;</hi> which, though it be ſuccinct, yet it is ſo perfect a Dilucidation of Truth, as may ſerve to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten all well-dispoſed Underſtandings to the perception of what Determination the Law gives therein; ſo that I may juſtly ſay of him, as <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> ſaid of <hi>Saluſt, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiſſimus eſt brevitatis Artifex,</hi> he being as rich in matter, as frugal of words. And though Arguments of this nature may ſometimes ſeem rather to kindle an angry flame, than to quench the fire, by reaſon either of unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
<pb facs="tcp:56948:3"/>of ſtating the Caſe, or of petulency of ſpeech in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Matter; yet I am exempt from ſuch fear in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this modeſt and ſober Treatiſe, by reaſon the ſtating of the Caſe as here ſet down, is acknowledged to be true by both Parties to the Controverſy; and for that there is not ſo much as a word of offence given in the ſtyle of the Author, nor any looſe intemperancy of ſpeech us'd therein, he ſpeaking nothing elſe but what falls directly under the conſideration of the Subject, as fit to be determined by the preciſe deciſion of Law.</p>
            <p>Nor do I deſign to preſent this, as a matter of Curioſity to the Reader, though the matter of Fact be <hi>de rarò con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingentibus;</hi> nor to preſent unto the Lady Objècts of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to frighten her with guilty Apprehenſions, or to tax her with the polluted myſtery of a Matrimonial-Bed, or the ſtain of Unchaſte Extravagancies; or to convene her before the great Judge of Heaven and Earth, who is ſo formidable to the ſence of Guilt; or to upbraid her with the inevitable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of her Ruine, which will enſue her Temerity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance: but to ſatisfie all Parties concerned, and even the whole World, in the Juſtice and Reaſon of the Lord <hi>Decies</hi> his Caſe, ſufficient to enforce the belief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unreſiſtible, even upon the moſt prevaricated Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. For your Lordſhip will not find in the Author's diſcourſe an umbrage of Rhetorical Flouriſhes, but a breviary of ſuch Arguments and Authorities as are of force to ſway the points in controverſie, and to turn the Objections out of all Laws in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:56948:3"/>Arguments to perſwade the contrary; inſomuch, that the ſaid Doctor's Allegations are ſo luculent, that words of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors could not, by Invention it ſelf have been put in order, more for our advantage; nor could Imagination frame a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of words more to the proof and approbation of our Cauſe, than are the ſaid <hi>Doctor</hi>'s most authentick Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being Authorities too clear to be denied or eluded, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no place to contrary Expoſition, and giving counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with Reaſon to whatſoever he propoſes to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, he clears the Text from the diſparagement of vain Cavils, the miſinterpretations of impertinent Gloſſes, and confutes the Lord <hi>Cooke,</hi> not only by the incompetency of his Authority, being neither Judge of, nor vers'd in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial Cauſes, but alſo by the inevitable Deductions from his miſtaken Poſitions.</p>
            <p>And finally, the ſaid <hi>Doctor</hi> lays down ſuch Principles, to beat out a path to the deciſion of the Cauſe in behalf of the Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> as that Judgment cannot be given in favour of Mr. <hi>Villiers</hi> without a manifeſt decadency from ancient practice, and deviation from all known Rules of Juſtice (as is generally conceived) whereby it is hoped that the Lady upon conſideration and reflection on the many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of her Seduction hitherto, and the Conviction of this Argument will be reduced to the modest acknowledgment of her fault; which is my earneſt deſire, who upon many Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations am bound not only to wiſh her happineſs, (as I do
<pb facs="tcp:56948:4"/>from the bottom of my heart) but by my best Endeavours to argue the ſincerity of my real Respects to her, from whence the Publication hereof chiefly proceeds, and to remain in the profeſsion I now make to continue during my Life,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble, faithful, and devoted Servant, <hi>R. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56948:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JOHN</hi> Lord <hi>DECIES</hi> of the Age of eight Years, was married by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> to <hi>Katherine Fitz-Gerald,</hi> (with the conſent of her then Guardian) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving compleated twelve years and a half of her Age; She about one and twenty months after the ſaid Marriage, diſagreed to the ſame, and on <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Eve laſt took to her pretended Husband <hi>Edward Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> the ſaid Lord <hi>Decies</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet alive, notwithſtanding the Inhibitions of the Court of <hi>Arches.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>QUAERE.</head>
               <p>Whether ſhe could avoid the firſt Marriage with the ſaid Lord <hi>Decies,</hi> or make Reclamation thereof?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56948:5"/>
               <head>ANSWER.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Conceive the Law to be ſo clear in the Caſe above ſtated, that there cannot ariſe any conſiderable difficulty among the Learned in reſolving the <hi>Quaere</hi> therupon propounded; Yet that the Reſolution thereof may be the clearer, and the more ſatisfactory to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all thoſe who are or may be concerned in the ſame, I ſhall bring it under the determination of a more general Queſtion, ſtated with ſuch Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Limitations, and Specifications, as will not only explicitly reſolve the ſame, but alſo anſwer and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch Objections as may ariſe out of ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Notions and Allegations that may be produced againſt the Negative Reſolution of the ſaid <hi>Quaere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion therefore is thus generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>Whether and when thoſe who contract Marriage, may depart therefrom by Reclamation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto I anſwer; That either ſuch Contract hath already paſſed into a Marriage, or <hi>in vim Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonii de praeſenti;</hi> either by preſent Conſent, or by Carnal Knowledge ſubſequent: in which caſe there is no departure therefrom by way of Reclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Or ſuch Contract hath not as yet paſſed <hi>in vim Matrimonii de praeſenti,</hi> and then firſt both Parties are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56948:5"/>at age of Conſent, to wit, the Man hath attained the age of fourteen years; or, ſecondly, both of them are under thoſe reſpective ages; or, thirdly, the one of them hath attained that age and not the other.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Caſe of this tripartite Subdiſtinction, where both Parties are at age of Conſent, the one Party cannot lawfully depart from the Contract without the conſent of both.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Caſe of the ſaid Diſtinction, to wit, both being under Age at the time of the Contract; it is to be underſtood whether both, or one only of them will reclaim before either of them attain to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent age of Marriage: And I conceive they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, whether they be equally diſtant from the ſaid competent Age; (as for example, He is Twelve years old, and ſhe Ten; or unequally diſtant, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thirteen and ſhe Ten:) or whether both, or either of them will reclaim after the arrival of both at competent Age as aforeſaid; And at this time ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving together at competent Age they may reclaim, as when at the time of the Contract of Marriage they were both equally diſtant from the Age competent at a different time, when one arrived at the Age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, having been unequally diſtant from a competent Age of plenary Conſent at the time of the Contract: or both, or either of them reclaims ſome time after the Accompliſhment of years competent for Marriage, and then they cannot, whether both
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56948:6"/>of them arrive thereunto at the ſame time, or at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times; as when the Man was Thirteen years of age, and the Woman Ten, the Man being by the revolution of a Year arrived at that competent Age aforeſaid, who then may reclaim, or thank himſelf for the loſs of that benefit; So that when they are of different ages from the time of plenary Conſent, it is in the pleaſure of the Party who firſt comes to Age, to diſſolve the Contract by Reclamation, which if he ſhall not then do, this Power is devolv'd to that Party who ſhall be then under Age.</p>
               <p>As to the third Caſe of the Diſtinction, where one of them hath attained the age of plenary Conſent at the time of the Contract, and not the other; the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that hath ſo attained that age at the time of the Contract may not reclaim; but the Party who was then under that age, and now hath attained it, may make Reclamation. So when one of Age contracts with one under Age, the Contract is immediately good as to both, and each of them bound to expect until the younger comes of Age, who if he then make Reclamation, the Contract of Marriage is diſſolved; but if he ſhall not reclaim, they ſhall be compelled by the Church to proſecute the Contract.</p>
               <p>I having thus ſet down the firſt Principles which relate to the Controverſie, and are of greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to the determination thereof, I ſhall now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56948:6"/>apply my ſelf more particularly to the very Caſe, and in the firſt place alledge out of the Decretals <hi>de Diſpon. Impub. Cap. de illis</hi> §. <hi>Mulier autem,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>Mulier autem quae poſtquam annos Nubiles attingit, ei qui nondum ad annos aptos Matrimonio venerat, nupſit, cum in eum ſemel conſenſerit, amplius non poterit diſſentire, niſi ipſe cui nupſit, in eam ſuum negaverit praeſtare conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</hi> And though the Gloſs may ſeem to derogate from the Text, ſeeming like the Gloſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> which, as hath been ſaid, corrupts the Text; yet I conceive that the Gloſs upon the words, <hi>ſemel conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit,</hi> having ſet forth <hi>quod multi contractus claudicant, &amp; ex una parte poſſunt tenere, &amp; ex altera non;</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding afterwards a diverſity by the word, <hi>Secus</hi> there ſubjoyned, where he ſaith, <hi>Secus in Matrimonio, quia illud vinculum non poteſt conſtare niſi ex duobus conſenſibus,</hi> doth not prejudice the Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> his Caſe: for he was at the time of the Marriage capable of giving a Conſent, being then of above Seven years of age, which he cannot recal until he come to the age of Fourteen, and will continue; unleſs he then, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after diſclaim the ſame; whence <hi>Dominus Abbas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Si alter pubes, &amp; alter impubes, &amp; impubes reclamat, non auditur ante aetatem Legitimam, ſi autem pubes reclamat, non auditur, ex quo ſemel conſenſit, &amp; ſic diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt hi</hi> §. <hi>quicquid dicat Gloſſa,</hi> either derogating from the Authority of the Gloſs, or putting ſuch reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Senſe thereon, as may reconcile it to the Text,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56948:7"/>by his <hi>diffiniunt, quicquid dicat Gloſſa,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, This Gloſs doth not hinder, but that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be given, notwithſtanding the ſame, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Reclamation of the party who was at age at the time of the Contract. And as for the words of the Reaſon given by the Gloſs, <hi>quia illud vinculum non poteſt conſtare niſi ex duobus conſenſibus,</hi> I conceive that the word <hi>Conſtare</hi> bears the ſenſe of the word <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere,</hi> as it doth in <hi>Pandects, L.</hi> 68. <hi>&amp; L.</hi> 98. <hi>in fi. de Solut.</hi> So that the ſenſe of the whole clauſe is, That ſuch Marriage cannot conſiſt or continue, without the conſent of the <hi>Minor</hi> be continued when he comes of age.</p>
               <p>And as to the Authority of the Gloſs, it hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been held in great veneration, in ſo much that it hath been called <hi>Juris Idolum. Sallicetus</hi> ſaid, that we ought, <hi>adhaerere Authoritati Gloſſae, ſicut Bononienſes Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp; ſicut ducens navem inhaeret temoni;</hi> Nay further, <hi>Anthonius Curſetus</hi> ſaith, <hi>de Authoritate Gloſſae, illam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Doctoribus antecellere;</hi> yet in limitation of his words, and explication of what honour hath been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Gloſs by the former Quotations, he ſubjoyneth theſe words, <hi>Scilicet Gloſſae Authoritatem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecellere, hoc eſt, ſingulis partitivè, non ſimul ſumptis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, I confeſs that in the <hi>deciſiones Parliamenti Delphin. quaeſt.</hi> 39. ſet forth by <hi>Guido Papae,</hi> termed <hi>Excellentiſsimus Juris utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Monarcha,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Opinio Gloſſae magnae eſt Authoritatis;</hi> but it is, as there ſet forth,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56948:7"/>
                  <hi>Ubi corroborata eſt communi Doctorum Opinione;</hi> for the Gloſs never prevails againſt the common Opinion, or the expreſs Determination of the Text, though <hi>in cauſae arbitralis definitione,</hi> the Opinion of the Gloſs is allowed, as it was in a Judgment in a Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Dolphinat 1453, and in the year 1456, in a Cauſe there depending between <hi>Claudius Conſtanus</hi> and one <hi>Boccagius:</hi> whence it is, that <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Calvinus</hi> the Civilian, <hi>alias Kahel Wateranus ad voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulum; Gloſſa,</hi> ſaith, <hi>quotidie, &amp; in Scholis, &amp; in Judiciis, Gloſſas impugnari refelliquè videmus, niſi enim vel jure, vel rationibus funditùs nitatur, &amp; à textu non diſsideat, minimè ſequenda; nam ubi Textus expreſsi ſunt, ibi nulla eſt dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio, nec ad Gloſſam reſpiciendum:</hi> But that the <hi>Cap. de illis,</hi> is expreſs, plain, and clear, being written from <hi>Alexander</hi> the third to the Biſhop of <hi>Bath,</hi> will be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after proved by the Teſtimony of <hi>Marchantius</hi> in his Anſwer to a Queſtion upon the very like Caſe with Ours. In the mean time let it be obſerved, that the <hi>Cap. de illis,</hi> being written by the ſaid <hi>Alexander,</hi> and directed to the Biſhop of <hi>Bath,</hi> muſt needs be taken to be Law in <hi>England. Baldus</hi> delivers the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in <hi>L. Ancillae,</hi> C. de Furt. <hi>Nam Doctrina Gloſſae nullam nobis neceſsitatem imponit, cum ſit tantum probabilis ut dic. Bartholus. L.</hi> 1. <hi>ff. ſi certe pet.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Kahel</hi> adds further, <hi>Quod autem vulgo jactatur, quod in Judican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do à Gloſſa recedi non debeat, id non eſſe verum poſt Abbatem Zaſius inculcat, caeterum ubi textibus deſtituimur, tùm Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56948:8"/>authoritas minimè contemnenda est, qua de re latè diſſerit</hi> Nevizanus <hi>in Sylva Nuptiali.</hi> And in this ſenſe <hi>Jacobus Butrigarius</hi> and <hi>Baldus</hi> are to be underſtood, when they ſeem to magnify the Gloſs.</p>
               <p>And it is alſo to be conſidered, that the Gloſs is many times miſtaken as to the underſtanding of the Law; as for example, <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>in prin. Fi. uti poſsidetis,</hi> ſaying, that <hi>utile interdictum</hi> was therefore granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>uſu fructuarii,</hi> becauſe there is only conſidered a <hi>quaſi poſſeſsioni:</hi> for the beſt Lawyers ſay, that as a Propriety is ſeparated from a Poſſeſſion, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a part of Dominion, and therefore it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly ſaid by the Gloſſary, That a <hi>uſu fructuarii</hi> did <hi>quaſi poſsidere,</hi> viz. <hi>L. permiſceri, de acq. poſſ. &amp; Barth. in L. naturaliter in prin. Feod. &amp; ibi; Jaſ. Num.</hi> 18. Whereby it appears the remedy of that Interdict is not granted to a <hi>uſu fructuarii</hi> in reſpect of a <hi>quaſi poſſeſsion,</hi> but <hi>inſpectâ vera poſſeſsione,</hi> wherein the <hi>uſus fruite</hi> is, if there happen to be any diſturbance.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Jacobus Menochius</hi> under the title <hi>De Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda Poſſeſsione,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Accurſius,</hi> as famous a Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary as <hi>Johannes Andreas,</hi> is guilty of a very great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his Interpretation of <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>ff. Utrubi,</hi> and of the Rubrick of the <hi>Code, uti poſſ.</hi> and that his Gloſs is to be exploded, and himſelf to be derided, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he declares this to be the difference between the Inſcriptions, <hi>Uti poſsidetis, &amp; utrubi, ſcilicet,</hi> that <hi>Utrubi</hi> ſhould refer to an improper poſſeſſion of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vables,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56948:8"/>and <hi>uti poſsidetis</hi> to a proper Poſſeſſion; for beſides this, that it is the common Opinion, that the Poſſeſſion of Movables is a proper Poſſeſſion; it may manifeſtly be proved from the ſaid firſt Law of the <hi>ff. Utrubi,</hi> and the Paragraph <hi>Retinend. inſt. de interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi> whilſt <hi>Ulpian</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian</hi> call it <hi>Poſſeſsionem Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium:</hi> which Appellation <hi>in ambiguis ad ſermonis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietatem referri debet.</hi> Beſides, a <hi>uſus fruct.</hi> being <hi>pars dominii,</hi> it cannot be properly ſaid <hi>uſum fructum poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Menochius de Retinend. poſs. remed.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 245. declareth, <hi>Nec hic ego probo ſenſum Gloſſae.</hi> And the Gloſs in many inſtances is rejected by <hi>Baldus, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholus, Salicetus, &amp;c.</hi> as you may ſee further in <hi>Meno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius de Retinend. poſſ. remed.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 37. and in <hi>Maſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſub tit. Gloſſae.</hi> From whence it is that <hi>Abaſpelqueda tit. de Poenitentia diſt.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 107. ſaith, that the Gloſs is falſe, for two Reaſons; firſt, for declaring that to be Law, <hi>quod nullo Jure cavetur:</hi> whence I may forcibly infer with more Reaſon, his Temerity in declaring himſelf in this point contradictory to what <hi>Jure ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur,</hi> if he be to be underſtood, if the Gloſs were to be underſtood of perſons of above ſeven years of age. Secondly, for concluding againſt Cuſtom; for <hi>Conſuetudo est optima Legum interpres: Cap. cumdilect. de Conſuetud. L. minime. ff. de Leg.</hi> For if the Gloſs on the aforeſaid <hi>Cap. de illis,</hi> is to be underſtood againſt the Text, and the common Opinion, it is alſo againſt Cuſtom: for <hi>Martinus Abaſpilqueda de poenitentia diſt.</hi> 6.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56948:9"/>
                  <hi>n.</hi> 107. declares, <hi>Non eſt Textus illius ſenſus quem Gloſſa judicat, nec obſtat Gloſſa quia Textu decepta;</hi> ſo that it is not the Authority of the Gloſs that can decry, or bring into credit any Tenet againſt the Text, or the opinion of the Doctors. This therefore being the common Opinion in this Caſe debated, appears by the <hi>Roſella Caſuum</hi> fo. 404. n. 6. for theſe are the very words of the <hi>Roſella; Nota ſecundum communem Doctorum Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem in dict. Cap. de illis de diſponſ. impub. quod Contractis Sponſalibus inter unum puberem &amp; aliam impuberem, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pubes cum per venerit ad pubertatem, potest contradicere, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes autem qui conſenſit, non potest ullo modo contradicere;</hi> for which Reaſon the Propinquity ariſing <hi>ex Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio hujuſmodi rato, non conſummato,</hi> is not reſtrained by the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to the firſt degree, as is the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia Publicae honeſtatis,</hi> but remains an impediment <hi>uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad quartum gradum</hi> equally, as doth the Affinity of Marriage conſummate according to the definition of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> in the Extravagant <hi>ad Romanum; Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitur enim affinitas per Matrimonium per verba de praeſenti ante copulam ratione ſocietatis Conjugalis,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Coſmus Piſtorienſis, cap.</hi> 12 <hi>de Impedimentis Conſanguinitatis.</hi> And if it ſhall be objected, that the propinquity ariſing <hi>ex Matrimonio rato,</hi> ſeems rather to belong <hi>ad juſtitiam publicae honeſtatis,</hi> for that it is not contracted <hi>per copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</hi> I anſwer, that a far greater Bond is contracted, and of a far different kind from that of <hi>Sponſalia;</hi> for in <hi>Matrimonio rato,</hi> ſuch as this is, <hi>traditur facultas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56948:9"/>ad eandem copulam per quam Conjuges dicuntur una caro:</hi> for if Affinity be contracted by a Marriage <hi>per verba de praeſenti ante copulam,</hi> as hath been ſaid before; it followeth that they are made <hi>una caro ratione ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis conjugalis ante copulam;</hi> for it is neither the <hi>copula,</hi> nor the preſent hability <hi>ad copulam,</hi> that is always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit for the continuance of Marriage; nor doth the want of ſuch <hi>Copula,</hi> or of hability thereunto, ſet the other party at liberty. For the Exception of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, which is an impediment to Marriage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires three years experiment after Marriage before a Divorce can be ſued <hi>à vinculo Matrimonii;</hi> for <hi>Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias non Concubitus, ſed Conſenſus facit.</hi> And it is certain that a temporal Impotency is no diremption of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony; nor doth a Diſeaſe <hi>qui reddit hominem inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem multos annos ad copulam, dirimere Matrimonium. Vid. Henric. L.</hi> 12. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>n.</hi> 1. <hi>Zancheſ. L.</hi> 7. <hi>d.</hi> 104. <hi>n.</hi> 10. And to conclude this Point, <hi>Coſmus Philiarchus de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonio, p.</hi> 302. <hi>In Matrimonio rato traditur facultas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ad eandem copulam, per quam etiam Conjuges dicuntur fieri una caro.</hi> Which Doctrine is allowed by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, who ſay, that <hi>Sponſalia ab uno impubere alter àque impubere Contracta, ſunt partim rata, partim ſuſpenſa; Rata, quia durante ea minori aetate reſilire non poſſunt: Non Rata autem &amp; ſuſpenſa, quia, quamprimum impubes factus est pubes vel reſilire, vel ſponſalia ratificare debet, ſeu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsè ſeu tacitè, Pubes autem qui cum impubere contraxit contractui ſtare debet, ſi alter velit.</hi> And it is alſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56948:10"/>of the Caſuiſts, that the Law of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which grant power unto a <hi>Minor adeptâ puber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> to make Reclamation, doth only free them <hi>à com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſione fori externi,</hi> and not from the obligation in <hi>foro Conſcientiae;</hi> for certainly, as <hi>Zanches</hi> ſays, it would be a ridiculous thing in Conſcience to think, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together diſſonant to Reaſon to believe, that the <hi>Sponſalia</hi> of one under Age ſhould be valid under Age, and yet not oblige at all at the accompliſhment of years fit for conſummation of Marriage; nay, the Caſuiſts are ſo ſtrict in that caſe, that even where the <hi>Sponſalia</hi> are but <hi>de futuro,</hi> they enjoyn Penance to the Party reclamant, <hi>de fide mentitâ.</hi> vid. <hi>Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitan ad Cap. ſi inter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as to <hi>Sponſalia per verba de praeſenti,</hi> they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly ſo called, in reſpect of the Bond of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but in regard of the Execution of Matrimony: for <hi>Panormitan</hi> ſaith <hi>ibidem, Uterque ſpondet in futurum reſpectu executionis, ſed reſpectu vinculi promittit de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenti:</hi> for which Reaſon <hi>Divus Severus</hi> &amp; <hi>Antoninus</hi> in their Reſcripts have declared, <hi>Neque Matrimonium qualecunque nec ſpem Matrimonii violari permittitur, &amp; Diſpoſitio,</hi> (loquens de Matrimonio) <hi>verificatur in eo quod de praeſenti contractu eſt, licet non ſit copula ſecuta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo worthy of obſervation, that the Canons which rule this Caſe are more favourable to Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age than to the profeſſion of Religion or Teſtaments, inſomuch that at Seven years of age Matrimony may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56948:10"/>be valid <hi>quoad Obligationem Matrimonii,</hi> though the Parties who make profeſſion muſt be compleat Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years of age, and the perſons who make a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament muſt be Fourteen: and the Reaſon is too clear in the <hi>Ladies Practice, Quia natura magis &amp; citius inclinat ad Nuptias quam ad alios actus politicos vel pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> and therefore the Law doth expreſly make irrit the profeſſion of Religion and Teſtaments made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reſpective periods of Sixteen and Fourteen years, though in Marriage the anticipation of Seven years doth not invalidate Eſpouſals, or Marriage, <hi>quando malitia ſupplet aetatem.</hi> And agreeable unto this Doctrine is the Caſe ſet down in <hi>Aurea Armilla ſub vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulo, Sponſalia, N.</hi> 11. Two contracted Marriage being of unequal Age, the one being Eighteen years old, the other under the Age of Marriage, were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the degrees of Conſanguinity prohibited, it was therefore unlawful for them to conſummate Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age without a Diſpenſation: yet the elder of the two was forced to ſue out a Diſpenſation, thereby to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to keep the faith of his Contract, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards was compelled to conſummate the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; nay he was bound, ſaith <hi>Panormitan, facere quid poſsit ut Diſpenſationem haberet à Superiore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot forget to mention in <hi>Codice Legum Wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothorum, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 4. <hi>de Adulteriis,</hi> 2. <hi>antiq. pa.</hi> 71. printed at <hi>Paris; Si inter Sponſum et Sponſae Parentes, aut cum ipſa forſitan muliere, quae in ſuo conſiſtit arbitrio, ſicut
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56948:11"/>conſuetudo eſt, ante teſtes facto placito de future conjugio aut cum parentibus ejus quibus Lex poteſtatem tribuit, facta fuerit definitio &amp; poſtea puella vel mulier Adulterium commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe detegatur, aut alteri fortaſſè viro ſe deſpondiſſe, vel in conjugio ſociaſſe probatur unà cum Adultero ſive injuſto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito vel ſponſo illicito, quem ſibi contra priorem definitionem ſociare preſumpſit, in poteſtate prioris tradantur Sponſi cum rebus ſuis omnibus ſervituri, ideſt, tam mulier ipſa ſcelerata quam vir ille, qui illam Adulter aſſe vel Sponſaſſe, vel in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugio ſibi ſociaſſe dignoſcitur; in poteſtate illius cui primum praedicta mulier pacta fuerat ſervituri tradantur, vel de his quod voluerit faciendi habeat poteſtatem.</hi> And to conclude this point of the Gloſs, there is a Cenſure thereupon, wherein are expreſſed many hundreds of Errors, with an intimation of a more accurate and fuller Repurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof from many pernicious Errors: which Cenſure was publiſhed by <hi>Thomas Manricus,</hi> Maſter of the Apoſtolical Palace, <hi>anno</hi> 1575; after which (ſaith he) <hi>multa in Gloſsis intacta reliquimus non ideo quod ut vitioſa non ſint:</hi> whereby it is to be underſtood how little Authenticity there is in the Gloſs, eſpecially where it is againſt a clear Text, as we have proved, <hi>Caput de illis,</hi> to be; or <hi>contra communem Opinionem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> which impugn the Gloſs in this behalf.</p>
               <p>The next Objection conſiderable ariſeth out of the <hi>Deciſiones Rotae;</hi> which is indeed more in ſound of words, than can be juſtified or upheld by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities alledged for ſupport thereof: for <hi>Opinio Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56948:11"/>debet intelligi ſecandum jura quae allegant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Johannes Gutierres re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. §. ſui n. <hi>112.</hi> vid. Bartholum in L. non ſolum. §. ſi liberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones verba, n. <hi>7.</hi> ff. de libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. legat.</note> the words of the Deciſion 450 are the contrary of what is above ſet forth in the ſaid Paragraph, <hi>Mulier autem,</hi> and therefore emphatical enough againſt us in ſound, though not in weight of Authority: For let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Allegations on which they ground their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and we ſhall find that they make nothing againſt us, and do not in the leaſt juſtifie the ſaid Doctors, unleſs they reſtrain the generality of their words according to the diſtinction I have above ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of the <hi>Minor</hi> being above or under Seven years of age: if they ſpeak in this their Aſſertion of a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> under Seven years, I ſhall not impugn their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for it is out of the Caſe of the Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> he being at the time of the Marriage above the age of Seven years; but if they ſpeak of a <hi>Minor</hi> above Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years, none of the Authorities which they alleadg will reach to the maintenance of their Aſſertion; for they quote but two Authorities, that is to ſay the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put literas,</hi> and the <hi>Caput acceſſit de Deſponſ. impub.</hi> both which expreſly ſtate the Caſe of <hi>Minors</hi> under Seven years, and accordingly reſolve the ſame: for the <hi>Caput literas</hi> ſtates the Caſe of a <hi>Minor in Cunabulis</hi> thus; <hi>Cum quidam eſſet perfectae aetatis quandam puellam in cunabulis deſponſavit, procedente verò tempore, matrem pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellae cognovit, &amp; eam in uxorem accepit.</hi> And the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution there is; <hi>Si praefatus vir matrem puellae, antequam Septimum annum complêſſet, in uxorem accepit, matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56948:12"/>non diſſolvas, cùm deſponſationes hujuſmodi nullae ſunt, quae in cunabulis fiunt.</hi> This Caſe differs in two things from ours, for the <hi>Minor</hi> was <hi>in Cunabulis,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt Contract was void; and though the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> could not in that caſe, coming to ſeven years of age, obtain the Man by reaſon of Affinity contracted by the ſecond Marriage, yet the Mother was divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; which ſhews that the ſecond Marriage, not only in caſe of a <hi>Minor,</hi> being above ſeven years of age, but after, being under ſeven years, and afterwards ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at Seven, and then conſenting, is invalid; for which Reaſon the Man was divorced from the ſecond Wife, though not reſtored to the <hi>Minor,</hi> by reaſon only of the impediment of Affinity contracted: nay had the ſecond Wife been of a remoter degree to the firſt, neither Marriage could have ſubſiſted by the Law of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> not the firſt, <hi>propter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedimentum Affinitatis;</hi> or the ſecond, <hi>propter impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Juſtitiae publicae honeſtatis.</hi> And as for the <hi>Caput acceſsit,</hi> it ſtates the Caſe, and reſolves it to the ſame purpoſe; So that 450 Deciſion of the <hi>Rota Romana</hi> can make nothing againſt the Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> in this Caſe, unleſs the ſaid <hi>Rota</hi> had power to repeal the Rule of Logick, which prohibits the Inference of a Generality from a Particular. Again, It is in the Caſe of Doctors and Judges giving their Opinion, as it is with Witneſſes rendring a Reaſon for their Depoſition, wherein there is <hi>dictum,</hi> and the <hi>ratio dicti:</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56948:12"/>if the <hi>Dictum</hi> be inconcludent, and the Reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto annexed be valid, the <hi>Dictum</hi> is made valid by the validity of the Reaſon; but on the contrary, the <hi>Dictum</hi> is not valid, if the Reaſon thereunto ſubjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be not concluſive; as for example: If the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould depoſe thus: It is true, <hi>Titius</hi> did lend one hundred pounds to <hi>Seius,</hi> becauſe I heard it ſo report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Upon this ground his Teſtimony would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valid, by the failer of his Reaſon in point of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and it is as eaſy to determine, that the Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Rota,</hi> being incompetent to prove their Aſſertion, the ſame muſt fail; for, <hi>quod inest termino referenti, intelligitur ineſſe termino, ad quem est facta rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</hi> Hence it is that <hi>Navarrus de Deſponſ. Impub. n.</hi> 4. ſaith <hi>Nicholas Papa relatus à Gratiano, ex illa Clauſula in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra [ubi non eſt conſenſus, ibi non est conjugium] ſolum infert quod pueri in cunabulis exiſtentes non poſſunt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here Matrimonium, &amp; ita mens ejus fuit dicere, quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſus infantilis non ſufficit, quod omnes fatentur;</hi> and herewith agreeth the Civil Law, <hi>L. in Sponſalibus: ff. de Sponſalibus,</hi> where it is ſaid, That Marriage is validly contracted, <hi>ſi perſonae non ſunt minores ſeptem annis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one Objection more I would obviate, which is this; That <hi>Fornicatio est diſſolutio Sponſalium.</hi> To which I anſwer; That true it is that <hi>Fornicatio,</hi> is, <hi>Solutio Matrimonii,</hi> but ſuch a Solution as doth not depend upon the will of the Nocent party, but on the Conſent of the Innocent; for (ſay the Canoniſts)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56948:13"/>
                  <hi>Fornicatio ad Solutionem Matrimonii non pendet ex illo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus est culpa ſed ex alterius conſenſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There reſts yet one Objection more which now comes into my mind, which is taken from the <hi>cap. ſi inter. paragrapho, ſi vero inter;</hi> grounded upon theſe words, <hi>Matrimonium conſummatum fortius vinculum est matrimonio rato,</hi> (and that) <hi>inter vincula inaequalia fortius, &amp; ſi poſterius vincit:</hi> But theſe words being rightly underſtood, do not reach to our caſe; for that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph is in caſe where the <hi>Sponſalia</hi> were <hi>de futuro, &amp; non per verba de praeſenti;</hi> and it is raſhneſs from a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Caſe there defined, to collect this general Rule, which is ſeverely reprobated by <hi>Bartholus</hi> and <hi>Ledeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma dubio</hi> 13 <hi>de Matrim. caſu</hi> 2. for, as we ſaid before, <hi>Sponſalia per verba de praeſenti,</hi> are improperly ſo called, <hi>reſpectu vinculi matrimonii, ſed respectu executionis matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii:</hi> for <hi>Panormitan ad dictum, Caput ſi inter,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Uter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpondet in futurum respectu executionis ſed respectu vinculi promittit de praeſenti:</hi> And though it hath been ſaid, that the Marriage of Perſons under Age are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as <hi>Sponſalia de futuro,</hi> yet this is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>respectu executionis, non respectu vinculi;</hi> ſo that in our Caſe the <hi>Vinculum,</hi> and the Execution may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Conſent of the Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> when he comes to Age; but the Lady is indiſſolubly tied <hi>ratione vinculi,</hi> being above Twelve years when ſhe was married to the Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> and may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to conſummate the ſame Marriage, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56948:13"/>rather, for that the ſecond pretended Marriage was contrary to the Inhibition of the Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not be ſo valid or capable of the priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the firſt, according to the practice and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Court of Arches in <hi>England,</hi> viz. <hi>Clarkes practice, tit.</hi> 200. But further, both parties to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Marriage are to be puniſhed and corrected, as you may ſee in the ſaid <hi>Clarkes practice, tit.</hi> 199. <hi>de puniendis perſonis ſolemniſantibus vel contrahentibus matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium lite pendente ac contra inhibitionem Judicis;</hi> —And for that the <hi>Sponſalia</hi> celebrated between her and the Lord <hi>Decies</hi> could not have been diſſolved but by the Judges Eccleſiaſtical; Again, we ſay, that <hi>quod vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum matrimonii, matrimonium ratum &amp; conſummatum,</hi> are of equal force; and that ſo often as two incompaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bonds of equal force are contracted, the firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiceth the ſecond; and therefore it is, that <hi>frangen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Sponſalia jubentur cogi cenſura Eccleſiaſtica ab Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro,</hi> 3. <hi>C. ex libris Sylvani de Sponſalibus &amp; C. praeterea: eod. tit.</hi> That is to ſay, they who violated ſuch Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, are commanded by <hi>Alexander</hi> the third by Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Cenſures to performance. And where it is ſaid, that <hi>Matrimonium conſummatum fortius est vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum;</hi> it is to be underſtood, as we ſaid before, in the Compariſon between <hi>Matrimonium conſummatum,</hi> and <hi>Sponſalia per verba de futuro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus fully anſwered the aforeſaid Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall clear a miſtake of ſome upon the Statute
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56948:14"/>of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth concerning Marriages: For tho in the ſaid Statute it be enacted, that the ſecond Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage conſummate with fruit of Iſſue be to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of before any Marriage unconſummate, yet the ſaid Statute was repealed in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and did not recover ſtrength by the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or 2. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to the degrees of Conſanguinity, mentioned in the ſaid reſpective Statutes of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am to clear alſo another miſtake of thoſe who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo much upon reciprocation of Contracts in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Marriage; as if the inequality of Conditions in a Contract could not ſtand with reciprocation thereof; as for example: <hi>Titius</hi> ſells his Horſe to <hi>Seius,</hi> and delivers the Horſe, the other receives the money; yet, if in the Contract there be a clauſe of Retrovendition, there is a reciprocation of Contract, though the Seller may have the Horſe back again by vertue of that clauſe: Even ſo, though the Law im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the condition of Reclamation, yet the Contract is good and reciprocal until ſuch Reclamation be made.</p>
               <p>By what hath been premiſed it clearly followeth in the vigour of good Conſequence, how great a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and different effects there are between the puſilage of one contracting Marriage under Seven years, and the minority of one contracting above Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years: for in the firſt Caſe, the Juſtice of publick
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56948:14"/>Decency and Honeſty (as the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> term it) takes no place; but in the latter Caſe, there ariſeth <hi>impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum publicae honeſtatis</hi> ſufficient for Diremption of Marriage; ſo that upon diſſolution of Marriage by diſſent at twelve or fourteen years reſpectively, the party diſſenting cannot lawfully marry by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law with the Kindred relating to the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty within the degrees prohibited. And the Reaſon is, becauſe that if he be under ſeven years he hath no conſent to bind him, but if he had compleated ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years, he had a conſent. And for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if a Male under ſeven years marry with one of Age, the elder ſhall not be bound; but if the Male be above ſeven years of Age, and the Female twelve, ſhe ſhall be bound, though the Male hath his liberty to ſtand to, or depart from the Marriage: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith that celebrated Doctor, and famous Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, <hi>Petrus de Anchorano</hi> on the ſixth <hi>Cap. ſi Infantes de deſponſ. impub. Nota quod quandoque contrabit ſponſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Infans cum majore Infante, quo caſu, ſi non oritur ex parte Infantis, Juſtitia publicae honeſtatis, non oritur ex altera parte, ſecus ſi Sponſalia contrahat pubes cum impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere majore ſeptennio.</hi> Obſerve his Reaſon, <hi>quia pubes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciter obligatur, impubes verò poteſt per poenitentiam reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerve a former deciſion of the Caſe.</note>Furthermore, To ſhew that Deciſions of this Controverſie in favour of my Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> are not wanting, hearken to the words of <hi>Panormitan, Cap.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56948:15"/>ex literis de deſponſ. impub. Deciditur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor non potest diſsentire, ſed minor factus major:</hi> whence he concludes, that <hi>Major contrahens cum minore tenetur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectare minorem donec perveniat ad aetatem legitimam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although what hath been ſaid is ſufficient to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this Aſſertion upon an authentick Foundation, yet out of the Spring-tyde of Legal Proofs I ſhall at this time, out of a greater number (which for want of time I cannot now inſiſt upon) bring in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of other Authors, as well Caſuiſts as Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, without any unneceſſary enlargement, to ſhew further the Conſent of Common Opinion in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half;</p>
               <p>And firſt I begin with <hi>Dominus Cataneus, vocabulo Sponſalia p.</hi> 416. <hi>qui legitima celebravit ſponſalia; tenetur ſub reatu laethalis criminis procedere ad ſolemnizationem Matrimonii in facie Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hoſtienſis <hi>de desp. impub. n.</hi> 11. <hi>Sin autem pubes cum impubere contraxit, tenetur pubes expectare donec impubes veniat ad legitimos annos, ligatur enim adeo pubes quod non poteſt reprobare ſemel probatum, minor tamen veniens ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos legitimos ſi non conſenſerit poterit reſilire;</hi> (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) <hi>cum enim ſemel conſenſerit pubes, ſcilicet per ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba de praeſenti.</hi> The Reaſon is this; <hi>Pubes fortius obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur quâm impubes, quia maturioris conſilii eſt, plerunque enim aetas impuberis quod videat, ignonat, &amp; ſciens, fallere non videatur.</hi> Wherefore let no Man wonder at the Reaſon why the Lady ſhould be more obliged than
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56948:15"/>the Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> whilſt he hath a power reſerved to himſelf of diſſenting. <hi>Summa Armilla ſub vocabulo, ſponſalia, Impubes cum pervenerit ad aetatem debitam potest contradicere, pubes autem nunquam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boych</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Extra, de Desponſ. &amp; Matr. Cap. perquiſivit,</hi> quoting <hi>Gofridus in ſumma tit. eod. Indiſtinctê pubes diſſentiens cogi debet ad celebrandum:</hi> Whence it follows, that notwithſtanding the pretended ſecond Marriage, the Lady <hi>Decies</hi> is compellable to reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord <hi>Decies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arnoldus Corvinus <hi>Juris Canonici lib.</hi> 2. <hi>tit.</hi> 12. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahere ſponſalia poſſunt omnes tâm puberes, quàm impuberes qui ſeptennium exceſſerunt. C. acceſsit</hi> 5. <hi>de desponſ. impub. quia voluntas quae in naturali conſenſu quieſcit, in eos, qui ſeptem annorum complêrunt aetatem, cadit; L. ſi Infanti</hi> 18. §.<hi>ult. &amp; L. potuit.</hi> 5. <hi>C. de Jure de lib. Ante ſi contraxerint poſt ſeptimum annum legitimo conſenſu, C. duo pueri,</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; ibi Abb. eod. vel cohabitatione.</hi> C. <hi>literas</hi> 4. §. <hi>fin.</hi> C. <hi>acceſsit.</hi> 5. <hi>verſi conſenſus.</hi> C. <hi>duo pueri</hi> 12. <hi>eod. vel nixu ad coitum.</hi> C. <hi>juvenis</hi> 3. <hi>hic.</hi> C. <hi>fraternitati</hi> 7. <hi>de eo qui cogn. conſ. accedente convaleſcunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marchantius de Matrim. responſ. ad</hi> 2. <hi>quaeſt. Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo ad ſecundum: Dominam A. B. contrahentem poſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos pubertatis cum Domino,</hi> C. D. <hi>impubere ſive ante puber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem</hi> C. D. <hi>ſive post permanente conſenſu</hi> C. D. <hi>non poſſe reclamare vel reſilire: Eſt textus planus &amp; apertus.</hi> C. <hi>de illis de desp. impub. quod eſt Alexandri tertii ad Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonienſum Epiſcopum, ubi ſic habetur; Mulier autem quae
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56948:16"/>poſtquam annos nubiles attingit, ei, qui nondum ad annos ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos Matrimonio venerat, nupſit, cum in eum ſemel conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit, amplius non poterit diſsentire, niſi ipſe cui nupſit, poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ad legitimam aetatem pervenerit, in eam ſuum negave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit praeſtare conſenſum: ſed in propoſito caſu Domina</hi> A. B. <hi>poſtquam annos nubiles attigiſſet, nupſit Domino</hi> C. D. <hi>qui nec dum ad annos aptos Matrimonio provenerat: ergo non poteſt amplius diſsentire ex parte ſua, niſi Dominus</hi> C.D. <hi>ipſe reſiliat: Ratio autem cur puberibus poteſtas reſiliendi non concedatur, ſed ſolum impuberibus eſt, quiâ pubes cenſetur habere plenam perfectam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aetatem &amp; prudentiam ad delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum, non ſic vero impubes qui cum eo tempore quo ducit, non ſit aptus Matrimonio &amp; Generationi, ejus conſenſus datus ante pubertatem non cenſetur perfectus, niſi vel ratificetur poſt pubertatem adeptam, vel ſaltem perſeverare cenſetur; Quam rationem eximpubere Judicat.</hi> C. <hi>de illis, ſupra cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Corporis ſui ad generationem, cenſetur quidem modo illam dare, ita tamen ut plena poſſeſsio tantum pro tempore quo erat aptus generationi accipiatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Henricus Boych <hi>in tertio Caſu, ſcilicet, Quando alter contrahentium Spónſalia eſt pubes &amp; alter impubes refert. Aut quaeris utrum ille qui erat pubes tempore ſponſaliorum poſsit reclamare: &amp; dic quod non, ut hic, in §. Mulier autem, aut ille qui erat impubes: Nunc verò factus pubes: &amp; dic, quod ſic: dummodo in eo tempore quo pubeſcit vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continenti poſt reclamaverit: ut in Paragrapho allegant, ſi vero, unde quando pubes cum impubere contrahit, ſtatim te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Sponſalia quoad utrumque, &amp; uterque expectare tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56948:16"/>quo uſque impubes ad pubertatem perveniat, &amp; tunc ſi reclamat, ſolvuntur ſponſalia, ſi non reclamaverit, ab Eccleſia contrahere compelluntur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may now appear out of the aforegoing diſcourſe to the full ſatisfaction of all perſons, whoſe Intereſt will give them leave to comply with Reaſon and Authority, the greateſt Patron of Belief, that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the ſubſequent Recapitulation of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are moſt true: <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> (as repreſented in the foregoing Caſe) is ſo far obliged by the Marriage had and ſolemnized <hi>in facie Eccleſiae</hi> by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that he cannot make Reclamation thereof before he ſhall attain to the age of Fourteen years.</item>
                  <item>2. That the Lady being above Twelve years of age at the time of the Marriage ſo ſolemnized, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, could not either in Law or Conſcience, neither can ſhe hereafter reclaim, or depart from the ſaid Marriage, until Reclamation be made by the ſaid Lord of <hi>Decies</hi> at his age of Fourteen years: wherefore there is no Reaſon ſhe, being of Age at the time of the Contract, ſhould be at her own diſpoſal, whilſt he is bound not to diſpoſe of himſelf.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Lady <hi>Decies</hi> in Conſcience in bound, and by Law may be compelled to cohabit with the ſaid Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> if he ſhall think fit to aſſociate himſelf at his age of Fourteen.</item>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56948:17"/>
                  <item>4. That ſhe ought to have been ſequeſtred, and ſtill ſhould be ſequeſtred <hi>pendente lite,</hi> which undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly the Judges will do upon due requiſition.</item>
                  <item>5. That no Marriage againſt the particular Inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the Church ought to be priviledged, or to prejudice a former Marriage lawfully ſolemnized.</item>
                  <item>6. That the Conſequence of allowing the Lady <hi>Decies</hi> to continue in Cohabitation with Mr. <hi>Villiers</hi> would be extreamly injurious to my Lord of <hi>Decies,</hi> and a pernicious example and effect to the Publick.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For which Reaſons it is hoped, that no Man, who was not a Counſeller in the Deſign of the ſecond Marriage, will approve of it in the <hi>post</hi> fact, or will think that it is to be countenanced under the umbrage of a <hi>fieri non debet, ſed factum valet:</hi> for that ſentence of Law, though in ſome Caſes it might make good that which was otherwiſe unlawful, yet it doth not hold to the prejudice of a third perſon; nor can it make that void, which in it ſelf is indiſſoluble and cannot conſiſt therewith, unleſs <hi>priority</hi> of Contract ſhould yeild to <hi>poſteriority;</hi> or the Law 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Marriages were Repealed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Dated <date>the 30th of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1676.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Dud. Loftus.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:56948:17"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
